Guide to the Jack G. Shaheen Papers TAM.535
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jack G. Shaheen Papers
1940-2018
1968-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Shaheen, Jack G., 1935-2017
Shaheen, Bernice Marie Rafeedie, 1936-
TAM.535
104 Linear Feet in 79 record cartons, 5 manuscript boxes, 1 tall manuscript box, 3 half manuscript boxes, 8 oversize flat boxes, 3 packing boxes, 4 oversize folders, and 3 map case folders
515 DVDs
621 VHS
26 CDs
11 MiniDV
4 Blue-ray
46 CD-ROM
30 film reels
1 2_Inch_Videoreel
162.85 Megabytes in 4 computer files
26 audiocassettes
114 DVD-R
16 Gigabytes in 2 flash drives
2 3.5" floppy disks
36 Megabytes in 30 5.25" floppy disks
Dr. Jack G. Shaheen (1935-2017) was a professor, author, and consultant who dedicated his career to identifying and contesting stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims in American media. The Jack G. Shaheen Papers date from 1943 to 2012 and document Shaheen's scholarly and popular writing and research in media analysis; his media accountability activism through the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC); and his consultation work on legal cases as well as the entertainment industry. The collection includes printed and born-digital draft and revised writings, speeches, notes, research and subject files, reports, correspondence, and sound and video recordings of Shaheen's speeches. The collection also contains material collected by Shaheen, including comic books; editorial cartoons; recordings of movies, television shows, and cartoons; magazines; posters; advertisements; toys; games; and other ephemera, which depict Arabs and Muslims in American popular culture and mass media from the late 19th to the 21st centuries.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jack G. Shaheen in 2010; additional materials were donated by Shaheen in 2011 and 2012, and by Bernice Shaheen in 2018, 2019, March 2020, and March 2023. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2010.037, 2011.074, 2012.002, 2012.091, 2017.058, 2018.066, 2018.142, 2019.082, 2020.022, and 2023.066
Appraisal
Duplicative clippings, periodicals, and video recordings were deaccessioned. One blank floppy disk was deaccessioned.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series and subseries:
Series I. Writings
Subseries I.A. Books and Documentary
Subseries I.B. Scholarly Articles and Book Chapters
Subseries I.C. Popular News Articles and Op-Eds
Subseries I.D. Film Reviews
Subseries I.E. Speeches, Lectures, and Presentations
Subseries I.F. Articles and Recordings Featuring, Interviewing, or Citing Shaheen
Series II. Media Research and Advocacy Files
Subseries II.A. Research Files
Subseries II.B. Advocacy and Media Accountability Files
Series III. Consulting Files
Subseries III.A. Entertainment Productions
Subseries III.B. Legal Case Files
Series IV. Subject Files
Series V. Study Artifacts and Ephemera
Series VI. Video Recordings and Films
Series VII. 2018 Accretion
Series VIII. 2020 Accretion
Biographical Note
Dr. Jack G. Shaheen (1935-2017) was a professor, author, and consultant who dedicated his career to identifying and contesting stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims in American media. His research analyzes the origins of these stereotypes, their persistence, the ways in which they affect perceptions of Arabs and Muslims in society, and presents solutions to counter them effectively. He was a professor emeritus of Mass Communications at Southern Illinois University at Edwardsville, Illinois where he taught between 1969 and 1994, and was a Fulbright lecturer in Mass Communications at the American University of Beirut in 1974 and 1975 and at the University of Jordan in 1982.
Shaheen began his research into Arab stereotypes in 1974 and collected materials which contained Arab stereotypes, both negative and positive. He wrote books, popular and scholarly articles, and op-eds, and lectured at colleges and universities, private institutions, and at conferences and conventions. After the events of September 11, 2011, he documented and fought stereotypes of Muslims as well. His books include The TV Arab (1984), Guilty: Hollywood's Verdict on Arabs after 9/11 (2008), and Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People (2001), which was produced as a documentary in 2006. Shaheen worked as a consultant on legal cases and in the entertainment industry, most notably on the films Three Kings (1999) and Syriana (2005).
Custodial History
Roughly 73 linear feet of video recordings (VHS cassettes and DVDs) and films were separated from the paper materials in 2011 and a video collection (VIDEOS.015) was created for these materials. In 2015, the VHS cassettes and DVDs were deaccessioned from the collection and sent to the Hagop Kevorkian Center for Near Eastern Studies and the Asian/Pacific/American Institute at NYU. Commercially available titles were returned to the Tamiment Library and reincorporated into the collection in June 2017. In October 2017 two boxes of material were sent to the Tamiment Library from the Asian/Pacific/American Institute containing sound recordings, commercial video recordings, and paper material.
Scope and Contents
The Jack G. Shaheen Papers date from 1943 to 2012, with the bulk of the material dating between 1968 and 2002, and document Shaheen's scholarly and popular work in media and cultural analysis. The collection includes Shaheen's writings, speeches, research files, notes, and correspondence in print, audiovisual, and born-digital formats. Shaheen's media accountability work, carried out both independently and with the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC), is also represented through correspondence, writings, research, case files, and written reports. The bulk of the collection includes material collected by Shaheen which depicts Arabs and Muslims in American popular culture and mass media from the late 19th to the 21st century, much of which he used in his writings and speeches. These materials include recordings of movies, television episodes, cartoons, and music videos; comic books; editorial cartoons; motion picture posters and stills; advertisements; video and board games; film and television scripts; a Halloween mask; t-shirts; toys; and other ephemera.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Materials in Series VI are unavailable for playback.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Materials
Materials received as part of accession 2012.002 were separated from the collection and a non-print poster collection was created for them. These materials were not arranged or described and were reincorporated into the collection in June 2017. Roughly 73 linear feet of video recordings (VHS cassettes and DVDs) and films were separated from the paper materials in 2011 and a video collection (VIDEOS.015) was created for these materials. In 2015, the VHS cassettes and DVDs were deaccessioned from the collection and sent to the Hagop Kevorkian Center for Near Eastern Studies and the Asian/Pacific/American Institute at NYU. Commercially available titles were returned to the Tamiment Library and reincorporated into the collection in June 2017. 16 linear feet of books were separated from the collection and added to the Bobst Library's general collection in June 2017. Material protected under attorney work-product doctrine was removed from the collection and returned to the donor in June 2017. In 2018, artifacts and off-air recordings were returned to the donor.
Manuscripts for publication.; Research notes.; Arabs in popular culture -- United States.; Comic books.; Clippings (information artifacts); Stereotypes (Social psychology) in mass media -- United States.; Arabs in motion pictures -- United States.; Stereotypes (Social psychology) in motion pictures -- United States.; Arabs on television -- United States.; Videocassettes.; DVDs.; Disney characters -- History and criticism.; Muslims in motion pictures -- United States.; Muslims in popular culture -- United States.; Shaheen, Jack G., 1935-2017; Shaheen, Bernice Marie Rafeedie, 1936-; American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee
- Series I. Writings, 1968-2012; 15.75 Linear Feet in 12 record cartons, two oversize flat boxes, one manuscript box, and two half manuscript boxes; 8 DVDs; 2 VHS; 2 CDs; 8 MiniDV; 1.35 Megabytes in two documents; 6 audiocassettes
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in six subseries:
  Subseries I.A. Books; Subseries I.B. Scholarly Articles and Book Chapters; Subseries I.C. Popular News Articles and Op-Eds; Subseries I.D. Film and Television Reviews; Subseries I.E. Speeches, Lectures, and Presentations; and Subseries I.F. Articles and Recordings Featuring, Interviewing, or Citing Shaheen.
  Subseries I.A., I.B., and I.E. are arranged in alphabetical order by title of work. Subseries I.C., I.D., and I.F. have not been further arranged beyond the subseries level.
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents Shaheen's work as an author and critic, and contains print and born-digital versions of his writings. Included in this series are draft and published versions of book manuscripts, articles, speeches, and film reviews, with clippings of articles quoting Shaheen or citing his work. Files for individual titles contain Shaheen's research for the work, draft and published versions, correspondence with publishers and collaborators, and administrative documentation. Sound and video recordings are present for some of Shaheen's speeches, lectures, and panel appearances and for the Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People documentary.
  - Subseries I.A. Books and Documentary, 1968-2008; 2001-2008; 7.25 Linear Feet in seven record cartons, one half manuscript box, and three oversize folders; 4 DVDs; 2 VHS; 1.27 Megabytes in one document
    This subseries documents Shaheen's work on his books critiquing American television and films, in particular Hollywood's depictions of Arabs and Muslims. Titles represented in this subseries include Guilty: Hollywood's Verdict on Arabs after 9/11 (2008), Nuclear War Films (edited by Shaheen, 1978), Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People (2001), and The TV Arab (1984). This series also contains notes for a planned follow-up to The TV Arab, titled The TV Arab Revisited. Materials include print and born-digital copies of draft and revised manuscripts, correspondence with publishers and collaborators, research files, and administrative documentation. The bulk of the subseries documents Shaheen's work on Reel Bad Arabs, with both print and electronic drafts, and includes extensive research files on movies, filed according to topics he devised for the book, which include plot synopses, notes, and newspaper clippings of film reviews. Some of these files contain correspondence between Shaheen and staff of research institutions and film companies researching obscure and out-of-print films. This subseries also contains the script, video recordings, and posters for the Reel Bad Arabs documentary (2006).
    - Guilty: Hollywood's Verdict on Arabs after 9/11, 2007-2009 (Box 1, Folder 1-5, Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Nuclear War Films, 1968-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Clippings and notes, 2001-2008 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Contract, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Correspondence, 1989-2001 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Drafts, 2000-2001
      - Paper Files (Box 1, Folder 16-28, Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_535_ER_1
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Film lists, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Inventories, 1991-2004 (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Letters to publishers, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Media contacts, 1998-2001 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Introduction, 1991-2001 (Box 2, Folder 14-19)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Cameos, 1991-2001 (Box 2, Folder 20-116, Box 3, Folder 1-188)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Champions, 1991-2001 (Box 3, Folder 189-221, Box 4, Folder 1-72)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Egyptians, 1991-2001 (Box 4, Folder 73-182)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Maidens, 1991-2001 (Box 4, Folder 183-184, Box 5, Folder 1-57)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Palestinians, 1991-2001 (Box 5, Folder 58-101)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Serials, 1991-2001 (Box 5, Folder 102-125)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Sheikhs, 1991-2001 (Box 5, Folder 126-178, Box 6, Folder 1-50)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Silent films and short films, 1991-2001 (Box 6, Folder 51-66)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- Villains, 1991-2001 (Box 6, Folder 67-198, Box 7, Folder 1-32)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Movie notes -- X-rated, 1991-2001 (Box 7, Folder 33-34)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Notes, 1986-2001 (Box 7, Folder 35-36)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Page proofs, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 37-39)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Poster book, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 40, Box 64, Folder 11)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Posters, 2006-2008 (Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003, Folder 1, Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Presentations, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Promotion and reviews, 1988-2002 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Research, 1984-1997 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Script, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Selected film reviews, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Reel Bad Arabs: How Hollywood Vilifies a People -- Video recordings, 2004-2006 (Box 24, Dvd 5-8, Video 1-2)
    - The TV Arab -- Al Khaleej clippings, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - The TV Arab -- Book cover, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - The TV Arab -- Correspondence, 1977-2002 (Box 7, Folder 48-50)
    - The TV Arab -- Promotion, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - The TV Arab -- Publisher rejection letters, 1980-1988 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - The TV Arab -- Research, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - The TV Arab -- Reviews, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 54-56)
    - The TV Arab -- Typescript, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 57-58)
    - The TV Arab Revisited, 1987-1998 (Box 7, Folder 59-60, Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Subseries I.B. Scholarly Articles and Book Chapters, 1974-2011; 4.35 Linear Feet in three record cartons and one oversize flat box; 81 kilobytes in one document
    This subseries contains drafts and published versions of Shaheen's scholarly articles and book chapters, as well as research files and correspondence. The writings in this subseries span Shaheen's career, and date from 1974 to 2011. Topics include the portrayal of Arabs in television, movies, comic books and strips, editorial cartoons, and animated cartoons. The bulk of the subseries documents Shaheen's work with Leonard Rifas on "The Comic Book Arab", a study of representations of Arabs in comic books. Files for "The Comic Book Arab" contain research files, drafts, and correspondence with Rifas. This subseries also contains research for an article on Arab representations in editorial cartoons, an electronic draft of "Arab and Muslim Stereotyping in American Popular Culture" (1996), articles on Disney's Aladdin (1992), and encyclopedia entries by Shaheen on stereotyping and Arab culture.
    This subseries is arranged in alphabetical order at the file level. The inventory lists box and folder numbers for an alphabetical range of titles. "Arab Images in Editorial Cartoons" and "The Comic Book Arab" are listed individually as they both consist of a large amount of material.
    - "ABSCAM: Arabiaphobia in America" - "Arab Images in American Comic Books", 1978-2002
      - Paper Records (Box 8, Folder 3-17, Box 66, Folder 6)
      - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_535_ER_3
    - "Arab Images in Editorial Cartoons", 1974-2011 (Box 8, Folder 18-31)
    - "Arab Images in Fiction" - "Cinematic Images of the Arab World", 1979-1993, undated (Box 8, Folder 32-45)
    - "The Comic Book Arab", 1984-1994, undated (Box 8, Folder 46-47, Box 9, Folder 1-30, Box 66, Folder 2, Folder 10, Box 65, Folder 12-14)
    - "The Detective Film in Transition" - "Hollywood's Eternal Villain", 1974-1999 (Box 9, Folder 31-41, Box 66, Folder 12)
    - "Hollywood's Muslim Arabs" - "You Are My Brother...", 1971-2007 (Box 10, Folder 1-54, Box 65, Folder 1, Folder 4)
  - Subseries I.C. Popular News Articles and Op-Eds, 1974-2012; 0.5 Linear Feet in one record carton and six oversize folders
    This subseries contains drafts and published versions of Shaheen's articles and op-eds for popular newspapers and magazines, as well as research files and correspondence. These articles span Shaheen's career, and date from 1974 to 2012. Topics include the portrayal of Arabs in American media and popular culture, in particular during the Gulf War (1990-1991); after the events of September 11, 2001; and during the wars in Iraq (2003-2011) and Afghanistan (2001-). This subseries contains articles on Disney's Aladdin (1992) and op-eds written by Shaheen for Newsweek, the St. Louis Post-Dispatch, and other newspapers.
    - Popular news articles and op-eds, 1974-2012 (Box 10, Folder 55-62, Box 11, Folder 1-3, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003, Folder 2, Box 65, Folder 7-11)
  - Subseries I.D. Film and Television Reviews, 1974-2000; 0.1 Linear Feet in two legal-sized folders and three oversize folders
    This subseries contains clippings of Shaheen's film and television reviews, the majority of which were written between 1974 and 1977 and published in The Daily Star, Beirut-Lebanon and the Metro-East Journal Magazine. The majority of these reviews are of films and television series in general, and do not focus on depictions of Arabs and Muslims.
    - Film and television reviews, 1974-2000 (Box 11, Folder 4-5, Box 66, Box 65, Folder 6)
  - Subseries I.E. Speeches, Lectures, and Presentations, 1979-2012; 1 Linear Feet in one record carton, one half manuscript box, one manuscript box, and one oversize folder; 2 CDs; 4 DVDs; 3 audiocassettes
    This subseries documents Shaheen's speaking engagements at universities and other educational institutions, cultural institutions, and conferences. Materials date between 1979 and 2012, and include printed notes and texts of speeches, slides used during presentations, administrative correspondence, ephemera for speaking engagements, ideas for speeches, and video and sound recordings of Shaheen. Topics include the portrayal of Arabs in American media and popular culture, and solutions for negative stereotypes.
    - Speeches, lectures, presentations, and slides, 1979-2012 (Box 11, Folder 6-48, Box 65, Folder 2)
    - Video and sound recordings of lectures and speeches, 1989-2011 (Box 24, Cd 1-2, Dvd 1-4, Box 72, Cassette 4-6)
    - Jack G. Shaheen Memorial Recording, 2017; cuid43007
  - Subseries I.F. Articles and Recordings Featuring, Interviewing, or Citing Shaheen, 1974-2010; 0.2 Linear Feet in one record carton, one half manuscript box, one manuscript box, and two oversize folders; 8 MiniDV; 3 audiocassettes
    This subseries contains clippings, and sound and video recordings of interviews with Shaheen, a transcript of the video interview, and articles citing his work, spanning from 1974 to 2010.
    - Articles featuring, interviewing, or citing Shaheen, 1974-2002 (Box 11, Folder 49, Box 12, Folder 1-6, Box Shared Tamiment MSXOS003, Folder 3, Box 65, Folder 5)
    - Sound recordings of interviews with Shaheen, 1994-1996 (Box 72, Cassette 1-3)
    - Video recording of interview with Jack and Bernice Shaheen, 2010 (Box 24, Video 3-10, Box 72, Folder 11)
- Series II. Media Research and Advocacy Files, 1968-2011; 4.5 Linear Feet in five record cartons and two oversize folders
  This series is arranged in two subseries: Subseries II.A. Research Files and Subseries II.B.: Advocacy and Media Accountability Files. Both are arranged in alphabetical order by subject, title of organization, or format of material.
  This series documents Shaheen's study of film and television depictions of Arabs and Muslims and his advocacy work to combat negative stereotypes of these groups. This series dates from 1968 to 2011, and contains research files on depictions of Arabs and Muslims in popular culture and files documenting Shaheen's advocacy work. The research files contain clippings from newspapers and magazines, stills from films and television episodes, and Shaheen's notes. The advocacy files document both Shaheen's independent advocacy work and that conducted with the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC). These files include ADC publications, correspondence between Shaheen and ADC members, and research conducted by Shaheen for the ADC.
  - Subseries II.A. Research Files, 1968-2011; 2.5 Linear Feet in two and a half record cartons and one oversize folder
    This subseries contains Shaheen's research files on depictions of Arabs and Muslims in American media and popular culture. This subseries dates between 1968 and 2011, and contains film scripts, teleplays, notes, and clippings. Clippings include articles from newspapers and magazines, as well as comic strips. Topics include negative stereotypes of Arabs and Muslims in film, television, comic strips, animated cartoons, and in the media. This subseries also includes Shaheen's clippings and notes on television episodes featuring Arab characters from 1986 to 2002.
    - Comics and cartoon files, 1977-2005 (Box 12, Folder 7-21)
    - Depictions of Arabs and Muslims in popular culture files, 1980-2008 (Box 12, Folder 22-34, Box Shared Tamiment 165, Folder 14)
    - Movie files, 1982-2011 (Box 12, Folder 35-47, Box 13, Folder 1-29, Box 66, Folder 9)
    - Television files, 1968-2005 (Box 13, Folder 30-44, Box 14, Folder 1-29)